32. Frida Kahlo's Paintings and Psychology. The Mexican painter Frida Kahlo, 1907 to 1954,
lived a life of extraordinary suffering. She caught a disease called polio when she was only
six. She was nearly killed in a bus accident when she was 18. The bus accident left her with
long-lasting injuries that caused her great pain for the rest of her life. Because of these
injuries, she was not able to have children. As a result, she suffered a painful miscarriage
when she was 25. The pain in Kahlo's body must have affected her paintings. Though she was an
energetic, active, vibrant woman, the pain often made her feel alone. The majority of her paintings
are self-portraits. Kahlo once said, I paint myself because I am so often alone and because
I am the subject I know best. She must have felt that her unique pain separated her from other
people. Kahlo often painted her face on the bodies of animals or other people. She painted
her individual suffering, but she also used her face to represent pain in all beings. However,
Kahlo also lived a life of passion and fun. She played sports in school, wore colorful clothes,
danced, studied, and loved. She was very proud of being Mexican and was politically active. These
characteristics are represented in her paintings. She uses bold colors, including lots of reds. She
also uses Mexican imagery, such as monkeys and parrots. Frida Kahlo took her pain, combined it
with her strong spirit, and turned it into art. Her paintings may make viewers uncomfortable
with their honesty, but Kahlo wasn't the type of person to hold back. If she could suffer and
grow, her paintings could make viewers feel and grow as well.